A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Director, Herbert Spencer Gasser, Correspondence, Series 2 FA143
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence, 1935-1961; 2; 4 boxes
  - M (Box 3)
    - Montreal Neurological Institute. Invitation and acceptance to speak 1957 May 15 22nd Annual Hughlings Jackson lecture. Title: "The Properties of Un-medullated Nerve Fibers with Afferent Function", 10 items
    - Muralt, Alexander, 3 items
    - M.G.H. Massachusetts General Hospital, 21 items
      Deals with term on Scientific Advisory Committee including 1952 December meeting.
    - Meek, Walter J. Many handwritten letters from W.J. Meek, 1935-1948; 74 items
  - N (Box 3)
    - Narodny, Leo H. on olfactory fibers in antenna of bee, 4 items
    - Newcomer, H. Sidney. On Electron Microscope Soc. of Am., 2 items
    - Nobel Prize 1952 material assembled by National Agricultural College of Bucks County, Pa. claiming Dr. Albert Schatz should have received joint recognition with Selman Waksman
    - Noordenbos, W., 2 items
    - National Academy of Sciences 1954 ballot
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 2 items
    - NDRC and OSRD National Defense Research Committee, 1940 December 31-1949
      Correspondence relating to activities as an official investigator; pledge of secrecy; correspondence dealing with interpretation of conflict of interests legislation. Correspondents include Vannevar Bush. Definition of Executive Order creating OSRD. Gasser resignation as Chairman of B-4C and appointment of Homer W. Smith. 1945. Presidential Certificate of Merit and ceremony held in New York Metropolitan area honoring recipients; photo at ceremony and copy of address by Julius Ochs Adler. Includes 17 receipts for mail of classified material and reprint: Science Vol. 110 (1941) pp. 649-651 "A Statement of NAS on AEC Fellowship Program".
    - National Society for Medical Research, 1950-1953; 35 items
      - Correspondence, news releases, copies of legislation dealing with anti-vivisectionist campaigns
  - O (Box 3)
    - Odoriz, Jose Bernardo, 2 items
    - Olsen, Robert E., 2 items
    - Osterhout, M.I., 2 items
  - P (Box 3)
    - Patton, Harry D., 5 items
    - Paul, John R. On portion of Kober Medal Acceptance speech, 2 items
    - Perkins, John A., 1 item
    - Perl, Edward R., 3 items
    - Petrzelka, Charles, 1 item
    - Physiological Society, 11 items
    - Planned Parenthood Federation. Statement on overpopulation, 1 item
    - Porter, Keith. Need for prompt publication of cytology papers, 1 item
    - Poynter, F.N.L. for Wellcome Historical Med. Library, 2 items
    - Prinzmetal, Myron, 5 items
    - Punt, A. On Festschrift honoring J. tenCate, 2 items
    - Pupilli, Giulio, 1 item
  - R (Box 3)
    - Ransom, James, 2 items (Box 3)
    - Rapaport, Ionel, 1 item (Box 3)
    - Rexed, Bror, 3 items (Box 3)
    - Richards, A.N., 4 items (Box 3)
      Includes copy of statement made as chairman of Committee on Medical Research (CMR) at joint Senate hearings concerning post-war program for scientific research. Includes long Gasser quote.
    - Ritchie, J.M., 4 items (Box 3)
    - Rivers, T.M., 9 items (Box 3)
    - Robertson, J. David, 3 items (Box 3)
    - Ronwin, Edward, 2 items (Box 3)
    - Rous, Peyton. quote from Pierre Curie on life of research, 1 item (Box 3)
    - Royal Society, 7 items (Box 3)
    - Royal Society of Edinburgh. Picture fund for James Kendall, 1 item (Box 3)
    - Rucquoi, Leon G., 2 items (Box 3)
    - Rudin, Donald O., 23 items (Box 3)
    - Russell Sage Foundation, 5 items (Box 3)
    - Rockefeller, David, 1940-1953; 35 items (Box 3)
      Includes suggestions prepared by Lindsley Kimball and a copy of notes made at meeting 1951 Dec. 10 of the Committee on Nomination and Review and a number of replies prepared in H.S. Gasser's office for David Rockefeller.
    - Rockefeller, John Davison, 12 items (Box 4)
      Memorial minutes prepared by Jerome Greene and H.S. Gasser and J.D.R. Jr's reply to the Board (duplicated copy). Also a short biography prepared by T.J. Ross with covering letter.
    - Rockefeller, John Davison, III, 1935-1951; 49 items (Box 4)
      Includes an exchange of letters about publicity for RI.
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1936-1954 1936-1944; circa 1 inch (Box 4)
      Concerns appointments to Foundation Board. Includes 1952 ed. of Charter and By-Laws; 1951 audit; summaries of 1953 Trustees' meetings. Also Foundation correspondence signed by Dean Rusk. Materials on Congressional probes of tax-exempt foundations as well as proposed I.R.S. regulations dealing with accumulation of income by charitable foundations.
    - Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (Box 4)
      Typescript of mss. "The relationship of RIMR to Education" with Appendix I and II which was presented in petition to U.S. Attorney General in relation to new immigration regulations 1949 October 20; also used in Annual Scientific report to Corporation v. 37 (1948). See also RG216.3. 7 items with Business Manager after retirement.
  - S (Box 4)
    - Sager, Ruth, 1 item
    - Saturday Evening Post, 1 item
    - Schaal, Eric, 4 items
    - Schmitt, F.O. with 2 enclosures, 4 items
    - Schuyler, R.L. Dictionary of American Biography, 2 items
    - Schweitzer, M.D., 1 item
    - Science, 2 items
    - Scientific Products. with enclosures, 2 items
    - Scott, Donald, 2 items
    - Shafroth, Morrison. From lawyers regarding a clients wish to establish a prize or grant program for polio research, 2 items
    - Siegle, Laurence W., 1 item
    - Sigma Xi. Election as honorary member of RI chapter, 1 item
    - Simon Brothers Management, 2 items
    - Sinclair, David, 1949-1960; 6 items
    - Smith, Edric, 1 item
    - Smith, Homer, 1 item
    - Smith, Paul Ferris, 1 item
      Includes tracing of Integrator test results.
    - Spies, Tom D., 2 items
    - Stanhope, William W. on advent of cathode-ray oscillograph, 2 items
    - Stevens, David H., 2 items
      Includes address on retirement from RF.
    - Stevens, Davis, Miller and Mosher, 1 item
    - Stewart, Florence, 1 item
    - Stockard, Charles R., 4 items
      Includes biography and clipping.
    - Swift, Homer F. 1937 advising HSG of appointment to Russell Sage Institute Board of Directors, 2 items
  - T (Box 4)
    - Tasaki, Ichiji, 5 items
    - Tomasch, Joseph, 2 items
    - Tunturi, Archie R., 3 items
  - U-V-W (Box 4)
    - Unesco, 1952 September 1; 5 items
      Includes 1952 Sept. 1 draft of letter: unable to travel to Montevideo.
    - Ullsvik, Bjarne R. Inability to travel to Platteville, Wis. to receive Distinguished Alumnus Award, 5 items
    - Van Slyke, Donald D. discussion of RI future paths, 1 item
    - Vastola, E.F., 2 items
    - Verzeano, M. with photographs, 2 items
    - Weaver, Warren, 1955 April 5; 4 items
      Includes Look 5 Apr. 1955 reprint "Can Scientist Believe in God?".
    - Weber, Hans H., 2 items
    - Weiss, Paul. encloses notes on Lorente de No, 1 item
    - Whipple, George H., 4 items
    - White, Philip R., 1 item
    - Williams, Hanley, 2 items
    - Windle, William F. enclosure on new journal Experimental Neurology, 3 items
    - Wolff, Harold G., 4 items
    - Woodward, Stanley. enclosure on presentation of honorary degree from University of Brussels, 1949 — transmitted through U.S. Department of State, 2 items
    - Woolley, D.W. Letter of esteem at retirement, 1 item
  - Y-Z (Box 4)
    - Young, John, 11 items
      Includes recommendation of support for.
    - David Barker at Hong Kong University
    - Zamecnik, Paul, 2 items
    - Zeiger, K., 6 items
    - Zotterman, Yngve, 3 items